<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<ebook name="APLeaveRules">

<para>
<para_name> INTRODUCTION : </para_name>
<para_desc>
The A.P. Leave Rules 1933 adopted to Telangana State are laid down in Annexure – III of Fundamental Rules &amp; Subsidiary Rules.
They are applicable to those who are recruited to services on or after 04.09.1933.
They are applicable to all State Govt. employees and not applicable to the contingent establishment and persons appointed on daily wages.
The Leave Rules 1933 are silent on certain matters like sanction of special kinds of leave viz., Maternity Leave, Study Leave, Hospital Leave, Special Disability Leave etc., and conditions for the grant of leave etc., For such matters which are silent in Leave Rules 1933, the provisions of Leave Rules in Fundamental Rules &amp; Subsidiary Rules have to be followed.
Leave is a permission granted to a Govt. servant to be absent from actual duty.
</para_desc>
</para>

<para>
<para_name>KINDS OF LEAVE : </para_name>
<para_desc>
• 1. Casual Leave.
• 2. Special Casual Leave
• 3. Compensatory Holidays
• 4. Earned Leave.
• 5. Half Pay Leave.
• 6. Commuted Leave
• 7. Leave not due.
• 8. Extra Ordinary Leave.
• 9. Special Disability Leave.
• 10. Study Leave.
• 11. Maternity Leave.
• 12. Miscarriage/Abortion Leave
• 13. Hospital Leave.
• 14. Leave for Hysterectomy Operation
• 15. Leave for Employment in Abroad
• 16. Paternity Leave.
• 17. Child Care Leave.
</para_desc>
</para>

<para>
<para_name>CASUAL LEAVE : </para_name>
<para_desc>
• Concept: A concession to Govt. Servant in special circumstances to be absent from duty for a short period.
• Authority: Instructions 1 to 6, Annexure - VII (Executive instructions regarding Casual Leave) of A. P. Fundamental and Subsidiary Rules vide Ruling 4 of FR 85.
• Admissibility: To all temp. / permanent employees.

• Crediting / Accounting:
i) 15 days per calendar year (G.O.Ms.No. 52, GAD(Poll.B) Dept., Dt.04.02.81).
ii) If appointed in the middle of the year, CLs should be credited proportionately.
iii) A register of CL should be maintained.

• Availing Procedure:
(1) By taking prior permission.
(2) In-charge arrangement should be made.
(3) HODs should intimate to the concerned Dept. in Govt.
(4) Can be availed in combination with OH, PH and SCL.
(5) Cannot be availed in combination with other leave, vacation and joining time.
(6) ½ day CL may be availed from 10.30 am to 1.30 pm (or) from 2.00 pm to 5.00 pm.
(7) For temp. employees, sanction depends on discretion of sanctioning authority based on the length of service. (G.O.Ms.No.999, Fin.,Dt.30.05.1959).
(8) Every Govt. servant is expected to attend punctually by 10.30 am. If there is late attendance beyond 10 min., late attendance should be marked and recorded in late attendance register. For every three late attendance, one day CL should be forfeited. The balance of late attendance in a year can be brought forward to next calendar year for forfeiting CL if there is no CL available in the previous year.
(9) Women Teachers can avail 5 days CL extra in addition to the CLs, OHs being availed of at present. (G.O.Rt.No.374, Edn.(Ser.V) Dept., Dt.16.03.96), The benefit of availing of 5 days CL extra in addition to the CLs and OHs being availed, to the Women Instructors (i.e. Technical Assistants, ATOs, DTOs &amp; TOs) working in Govt. it is / DLTCs in the state. (G.O.Ms.No.59, Labour Employment Trg. &amp; Factories (Emp.) Dept., Dt.22.07.2008)
(10) The benefit of availing of 5 days CL extra in addition to the CLs and OHs being availed to the Women Junior Lecturers working in the Govt. Junior Colleges in the State. (G.O.Rt.No.3, Higher Education (IE.I) Dept., Dt.05.01.2001).

• Limitations:
1. Total period of absence from duty should not exceed 10 days.
2. An officer is not entitled to take full amount of CLs in a year. (G.O.Ms.No.2465,Fin.,Dt.23.12.1959, G.O.Ms.No.2094,Fin, Dt.22.04.1960)
3. Frequent availing of CLs / Holidays by an individual should be avoided.
4. Balance will not be carry forwarded to the next calendar year
• Sanctioning Authority: Head of Office.
• Effect: Treated as duty for all purposes.
</para_desc>
</para>

<para>
<para_name>SPECIAL CASUAL LEAVE : </para_name>
<para_desc>
• Concept: A concession to Govt. Servant in special circumstances to be absent from duty for a short period.
• Authority: Instructions 7 to 10 Annexure VII ( Executive instructions regarding Casual Leave) of A .P . Fundamental and Subsidiary Rules vide Ruling 4 of FR 85.
• Admissibility: To all temp / permanent employees.
Special Casual Leave(Instruction 7):
(1) Summons to give witness in a court in which his private interest is not in issue -- As per the attendance Certificate.
(2) For Family Planning operations :
(2.a) Male - Vasectomy -- 6 working Days(G.O.Ms.No.257 F and P dt:05-01-81).
(2.b) Female - Tubectomy -- 14 Days(G.O.Ms.No.124 F and P dt:13-4-82).
(2.c) Male – For Tubectomy of wife -- 7 Days.
(2.d) Female - Insertion of Intra Uterine Contraceptive Devices -- 1 Day on the day of insertion and reinsertion (G.O.Ms.No.128 F and P DT:13-4-82).
(2.e) Recanalization (Both male and female employees) -- 21 Days or Actual period of Hospitalization which ever is less Plus Actual journey(to and fro period) Admissible to the employees who have less than two Children or who has lost all Male or Female Children after Family Planning operation.
(3.a) Female - Salpingectomy operation after medical Termination of Pregnancy -- 14 days(G.O. Ms. No,275 F and P (FW FRI) Dept. dt.15-05-81).
(3.b) Male - Salpingectomy operation for Wife -- 7 days.
(4) Post Operative Complications:
(4.a) Vasectomy -- Extended upto 7 days
(4.b) Tubectomy -- Extended upto 14 days on production of Medical Certificate.
• SCL can be availed for the 2nd time for the same period on production of MC mentioning the failure of previous operation (in case of Vasectomy and Tubectomy).
• SCL may be prefixed or suffixed to Regular Leave or CL and not both.
</para_desc>
</para>

<para>
<para_name>SPORTS : </para_name>
<para_desc>
• 8-A) 1. For participating in Sporting events of National or International Importance – not exceeding 30 days in a calendar year. (G.O.Ms.No.295 Fin FR-I Dept.dt.14-09-1964).
2. If exceeded 30 days – excess period treated as regular leave. Permitted to combine with Regular Leave but not with CL.
3. The concession shall not be allowed for the Participants on his personal capacity.
4. It is extended to Managers of Teams, Coaches and Referees(Go Ms.No.358 F and P (FWFR-I)Dept.dt.26-12-84).
5. SCL not exceeding 15 days may be availed for President /Secy. of National Sports Bodies recognized by all India Council of Sports(G.O.Ms. No.270 F and P FWFR-I Dept.,Dt.30-06-1976).
• 8-B) Participating in trekking expeditions approved by India Mountaineering Foundation, SCL not exceeding 30 days in a calendar year may be sanctioned.
• 8-C) Disabled Ex service men re-employed as Civilian in State Govt. services for appearing before Medical resurvey board for the reassessment of disability and to go to hospital for treatment --> 15 days of SCL (G.O.Ms. No.407 F and P FW FR-I Dept.dt.18-09-76).
• 9-A) For the recruitment in Territorial army or Auxiliary Air force. i) Attending for an interview, Medical exam followed by training etc. -One month or Less (or) ii) For participation in ceremonial Parades - One month or less.
• 9-B) For Registering the name under Reserve and Auxiliary Air-force Act-1952 i) Attending for an interview, medical examination followed by training - One month or Less
(or) ii) For participation in ceremonial Parades as a member of Air Defence Reserve - One month or less.
• 10-A) AP Secretariat Cultural Association Members for enacting dramas in mofussil areas – 6 days SCL in a calendar Year.
• 10-B) i) Principal Office bearers of Recognized service Associations(Represented on A.P. Civil Services Joint Staff Council) and 2 Office Bearers from each of the units in Districts and City – 21 days SCL in a calendar year. (G.O.Ms. No.205, Fin, Dt.08-06-1980)
ii) It will not be sanctioned in addition to any SCL allowed under Sports, Cultural Activities etc.
iii) The competent authority will have the discretion to withhold the Grant of SCL in exigencies of Govt. work (G.O. Ms. No.390 Fin, Dt.26-11-64).
• 10-C) Employees of vacation Dept.(Education, Judiciary etc.) -7 days of SCL in a calendar year Total SCL sanctioned shall not exceed 30 days if they participate in the Sports event. Competent authority shall have the discretion to withhold (G.O.Ms. No.47 Fin,dt.12-02-65).
• 10-D) To participate in Rallies, Camps etc. Organized by A.P. Bharat Scouts and Guides at State/National Level – 10 days of SCL in a calendar year (G.O.MsNo.112 Fin,dt.22-07-69).
• 10-E) Members of Institution of Engineers:
(a) For attending annual Meeting at Hyd. -7 days of SCL in a calendar year
(b) For attending annual convention to any part of the country - 10 days of SCL in a calendar year (G.O.Ms No.44 F and P FR-I,dt.05-02-06)
• 10-G) Govt. Servant participating in the cultural events in the National and International importance when he is selected by service /cultural associations recognized by Govt. - 30 days of SCL in a calendar year. ( G.O.Ms.No.360, F and P, Dt.24.12.1980).
</para_desc>
</para>

<para>
<para_name>SPECIAL PROVISIONS : </para_name>
<para_desc>
• For Donation of Blood: - 1 day of SCL on the day of donation on production of M.C.(G.O.Ms.No.137, M and H (EL) Dept.,Dt.23.02.1984).
• Women Govt. employees for being celebrated International Women's day on March 8th -1 day SCL on that Day (G.O. Ms. No.433 GAD(SW-II)Dept.dt.04-08-10).
• On account of presence of following infectious diseases in an employee’s house - small pox, plague, cholera, typhoid, acute influenza pneumonia, diphtheria, cerebra-spinal meningitis, measles - not exceeding 21 days of SCL on production of certificate from Medical Officer - extended up to 30 days ( Exe. Inst. 7 (a)(i) (ii) and Note (1) to (5)) Rescinded Vide G.O.Ms.No.10 F and P(FR I), Dt.24.01.1992.
</para_desc>
</para>

<para>
<para_name>COMPENSATORY HOLIDAYS : </para_name>
<para_desc>
• Concept: A Concession to a Govt. Servant in special circumstances to compensate the PH / OH which he has not availed due to called on to duty.
• Contexts:
1. Attending to duty on a public holiday (G.O.Ms.No.917,Madras Public Dept.,Dt.16.09.1902)
2. Attending to duty on an optional holiday already sanctioned (G.O.Ms.No.528,G.A.D, Dt.26.04.1961)
3. Attending to duty as turn duty (G.O.Ms.No.2036,Madras Public(Pol-B)Dept., Dt.11.08.1952).
• Authority: Annexure XII of A.P. Fundamental and Subsidiary Rules.
• Admissibility: To all temp. / permanent employees.
• Crediting / Accounting: Max. of 7 days or lower no. may be fixed in discretion by Head of Office. ( Memo. No.36/58-1, G.A.(Pol-B) Dept.,Dt.06.01.1958) •Effect: Treated as duty for all purposes.
• Availing procedure:
(1) by taking prior permission.
(2) Can be availed in combination with CL / Holiday / availed within a period of 6 months from the duty attended on a holiday (G.O.Ms.No.942, Public, Dt.17.10.1903)
(3) Can be availed by prefixing / suffixing. (Memo No.2690/Pol-B/64-2, G.A.(P.O.B.)Dept., Dt.03.10.1964).
• Limitations:
(1) Only 10 compensatory leaves should be availed in a calendar year.
(2) If possible, if the holiday is related to religious purpose the servant belonging to that religion should not be called upon to duty. (G.O.Ms.No.917, Madras Public Dept.,Dt.16.09.1902)
(3) Govt. servant touring on public holidays in connection with the performance of his duties is not eligible for this concession (Memo No.13112, Accts / 67-2, Dt.01.03.1958).
</para_desc>
</para>

<para>
<para_name>EARNED LEAVE : </para_name>
<para_desc>
• Authority: AP Leave Rules 1933, Rules 8-12, 17-18, 20-22
• Eligibility: All temporary and permanent
• Procedure of Earning / Crediting:
a) Regular:
(1) Earned for duty and leave period.
(2) 15 days adv. Credit on Jan and July.
(3) Max. Earning 30 days per year.
(4) Credit for one complete month =2 ½ days.
(5) Credit for fraction of month = 0.
(6) If an employee availed EOL, 1/10th of EOL period will be reduced in the credit of succeeding half year subject to max. of 15 days.(G.O.Ms.No.384,Fin.,Dt.05.11.1977).
(7) Max accumulation = 300 days. w.e.f.16-09-2005 vide G.O.Ms.No:232, Fin. (FR.I) Dept, dated :16.09.2005.
(8) Previous Limits for Max accumulation for Permanent Superior Employees From 01.06.1964 to 30.06.1983 - 180 days From 01.07.1983 to 15.09.2005 - 240 days.
(9) Previous Limits for Max accumulation for Permanent Last Grade Employees From 17.08.1967 to 30.06.1983 - 180 days From 01.07.1983 to 15.09.2005 - 240 days

a) Regular:
(1) Earned for duty and leave period.
(2) 15 days adv. Credit on Jan and July.
(3) Max. Earning 30 days per year.
(4) Credit for one complete month =2 ½ days.
(5) Credit for fraction of month = 0.
(6) If an employee availed EOL, 1/10th of EOL period will be reduced in the credit of succeeding half year subject to max. of 15 days.(G.O.Ms.No.384,Fin.,Dt.05.11.1977).
(7) Max accumulation = 300 days. w.e.f.16-09-2005 vide G.O.Ms.No:232, Fin. (FR.I) Dept, dated :16.09.2005.
(8) Previous Limits for Max accumulation for Permanent Superior Employees From 01.06.1964 to 30.06.1983 - 180 days From 01.07.1983 to 15.09.2005 - 240 days.
(9) Previous Limits for Max accumulation for Permanent Last Grade Employees From 17.08.1967 to 30.06.1983 - 180 days From 01.07.1983 to 15.09.2005 - 240 days
b) Temporary:
(9a). 8 days adv. Credit on Jan and July.
(9b). If appointed in the middle, first 2 completed months = 1 day 3rd month = 2 days
(9c). Max accumulation = 30 days.
(9d). The leave account should be recast after regularization. -> Availment: on Medical grounds/ private affairs :
(1). Not exceeding 180 days for permanent superior employees at a time subject to the balance in the account G.O.Ms.No.153 fin.(FR1)dept.dt.4-5-2010.
(2). Not exceeding 120 days for permanent last grade employees. G.O.Ms.No.329, Fin.,Dt.17.12.1982 and G.O.Ms.No.9, Fin., Dt.10.01.1983
(3). Can be availed on combine with other leaves.
(4). Public Holidays, Optional Holidays, and compensatory leave can be prefixed or suffixed. (Memo No.86595/1210/FR.I/7, Dt.29.05.1981).
(5). The existing limit of 180 days at a time on availment of commuted leave in conjunction with EL was removed. G.O.Ms.No.384, Fin., Dt.05.11.1977.

b) Temporary:
(9a). 8 days adv. Credit on Jan and July.
(9b). If appointed in the middle, first 2 completed months = 1 day 3rd month = 2 days
(9c). Max accumulation = 30 days.
(9d). The leave account should be recast after regularization. -> Availment: on Medical grounds/ private affairs :
(1). Not exceeding 180 days for permanent superior employees at a time subject to the balance in the account G.O.Ms.No.153 fin.(FR1)dept.dt.4-5-2010.
(2). Not exceeding 120 days for permanent last grade employees. G.O.Ms.No.329, Fin.,Dt.17.12.1982 and G.O.Ms.No.9, Fin., Dt.10.01.1983
(3). Can be availed on combine with other leaves.
(4). Public Holidays, Optional Holidays, and compensatory leave can be prefixed or suffixed. (Memo No.86595/1210/FR.I/7, Dt.29.05.1981).
(5). The existing limit of 180 days at a time on availment of commuted leave in conjunction with EL was removed. G.O.Ms.No.384, Fin., Dt.05.11.1977.

c) Leave Salary: Full basic pay prior to leave + all allowances HRA and CCA will be paid in full up to 6 months. (G.O.Ms.No.28,Fin.(FR.I),dt.09.03.11).
</para_desc>
</para>


<para>
<para_name>
Surrender of Earned Leave (Introduced from 13-08-1969) Vide G.O.Ms.No.238 Dt:13-8-69 :
</para_name>
<para_desc>
• Eligibility: Temporary / Permanent
• Availment:
(A) Permanent:
(i) 15 days for 12 months gap
(ii) 30 days for 24 months gap based on the balance available.
(iii) If balance is above 285 days on 30th June, gap need not be observed. Leave will be credited after deducting surrendered days. (Memo No. 50798/1063/FR-1/79-1, F and P,Dt.22.11.1979, Memo No.10472/C/199/FR-1/2009, Fin(FR.I), Dt.29.04.2009, Memo No.14781/C/278/FR.I/2011. Fin (FR.I), Dt.22.06.2011)
(iv) Only once in a financial year.
(v) Surrender Leave will be sanctioned from the date of application (Memo No.47064/1164/FR.I/91, F and P, Dt.20.01.92).

(A) Permanent:
(i) 15 days for 12 months gap
(ii) 30 days for 24 months gap based on the balance available.
(iii) If balance is above 285 days on 30th June, gap need not be observed. Leave will be credited after deducting surrendered days. (Memo No. 50798/1063/FR-1/79-1, F and P,Dt.22.11.1979, Memo No.10472/C/199/FR-1/2009, Fin(FR.I), Dt.29.04.2009, Memo No.14781/C/278/FR.I/2011. Fin (FR.I), Dt.22.06.2011)
(iv) Only once in a financial year.
(v) Surrender Leave will be sanctioned from the date of application (Memo No.47064/1164/FR.I/91, F and P, Dt.20.01.92).
(B) Temporary: 15 days after 24 months gap (G.O.Ms.No.221,F and P(FR.I),Dt.23.08.74, G.O.Ms.No.316, F and P(FR.I), Dt.25.11.74(Sup.) Memo No.47774/1177/FR.I/74-1, Dt.07.11.74(Class IV), G.O.Ms.No.393, Fin., Dt.31.12.75(all)) • Effect : Surrendered days will be deducted in leave account.

• Validity: Sanction order is valid for 90 days from the date of issue. (Memo No.14423/715/FR.I/91, F and P, Dt.20.01.92 and Memo No.27/423/A2/FR.I/97-1, F and P, Dt.18.08.97)
• Leave Salary:
(i) Claimed by considering 30 days/per month irrespective of claimed month. (G.O.Ms.No.306,F and P(FWFR.I) Dept., Dt.08.11.1974)
(ii) It includes Pay + OCA + HRA + AHRA + CCA. (Memo No. 64861/797/FR.I/71-1, Dt.14.07.72,G.O.Ms.No.25,F and P, Dt.05.02.96).
(iii) Conveyance allowance can not be paid (iv) HRA can be claimed to those who are Interim Relief will be paid (Memo No.31948/398/PCI/98-1,Fin, Dt.12.08.98) Debitable to HOA 010-018. Sanctioning Authority: As delegated.

Others:
1. It is extended to Municipal Employees, Public Health Workers, Non Public Health Workers, Zilla parishad, Zilla Granthalay, employees, Village Secretaries
2. Surrender Leave amount may be initially paid by the Foreign Employer for those who are working in Foreign Service, and the total amount have to be reimbursed by the parent department later on. (G.O.Ms.No.329, F and P(FR.I) Dept.,Dt.06.12.74, Memo No.49395/1219/FR.I/75-1,F and P,Dt.06.01.76). Encashment of E.L.s:
3. The employees are permitted to encash E.L. at the time of superannuation / death / Voluntary retirement/Retirement on medical grounds/ compulsory retired as a measure of punishment under APCS(CCA) Rules and has been enhanced to, from 240 to 300 days w.e.f. 16.09.05.(G.O.Ms.No.27,F and P(FWFR.I), Dt.19.01.76) G.O.Ms.No:232,Fin.(FR.I) Dept,Dt.16.09.2005, G.O.Ms.No.234,Fin(FR.I) Dept.,Dt.11.08.06 w.e.f.16.09.05( die while in service)).
4. EEL may be withhold for those who are facing disciplinary proceedings until final settlement which involves recovery of money (G.O.Ms.No.11,F and P(FWFR.I)Dept.,Dt.15.01.97).
5. EEL encashment is to be sanctioned by the parent department for those who retired in foreign service.
</para_desc>
</para>

<para>
<para_name>HALF PAY LEAVE : </para_name>
<para_desc>
• Authority : A.P. Leave Rules, 1933 Rules 13-15, 18, 23,23(a)(i)
• Eligibility: Permanent / (Temporary employees)*
• Crediting: 20 days for completed year No max limit for accumulation
• Availment: No max limit Can be availed on private affairs and medical purposes, can be combined with other leave Temporary employees avail this after completion of two (sup.) or one (inf.) years of service. (Temporary Govt. servants (Emergency) appointed under rule 10(a)(i) are not eligible to avail.) ( Memo No.20584/302/FR.I/74-1, F and P(FR.I),Dt.12.09.1974).
• Leave Salary: Half Basic Pay + Proportionate D.A. HRA and CCA in full upto 6 months No compensatory allowances after that. • Sanctioning Authority: as delegated.
• Leave Encashment: Encashment of EL and HPL shall be limited to 300 days. Superannuation pensioner, death cases, invalid pensioners are eligible. Amount will be paid as per formula (G.O.Ms.No.154, Fin(FR I)Dept.,Dt.04.05.2010)
• --[Formula =( Half pay + Prop DA)/30 * No. of days. ]--
• No compensatory allowances are admissible.
• If a Govt. servant suffering from TB/Cancer/Mental illness/Leprosy/Heart disease/Renal failure(kidney), HIV AIDS, he may avail HPL upto 6 months with full pay • Compensatory allowances will be paid in full upto 8 months.
</para_desc>
</para>

<para>
<para_name>LEAVE NOT DUE : </para_name>
<para_desc>
• Authority: AP LR Rule 15-C and 18-C
• Eligibility: All permanent employees
• Availment: When HPL is not at credit, it may be sanctioned on Medical Certificate only.
• Effect: Deducted from future credit of HPL account
• Leave Salary: Same as in HPL
• Limitation: 180 days during entire service.
• Recovery: If any employee resigns / retires voluntarily after availing this leave and before wiping off the minus balance, the leave salary paid for minus balance should be recovered. In case of medical invalidation / death, recovery will not be insisted.
</para_desc>
</para>

<para>
<para_name>STUDY LEAVE : </para_name>
<para_desc>
• Concept: Leave granted for the study of Scientific, technical or similar problems or to undergo special courses of instruction.
• Authority: FR 84
• Admissibility: For permanent Gazetted employees of min 5 years of service and 3 yrs of left over service Very exceptional for NGOs.
• Availment:
(1). May be granted for 12 months at a time and 2 years in entire service.
(2). May be combined with other leave.
• Effect: counts for increment, pension.
• Leave salary: Salary on half pay.
• Sanctioning Authority: Govt. Only.
• Limitations: If it is combined with leave with allowances, the period of leave should
not exceed 28 months.
</para_desc>
</para>

<para>
<para_name>MISCARRIAGE / ABORTION LEAVE : </para_name>
<para_desc>
• Concept: Leave granted to female Govt. servant to take hospitalization for miscarriage / abortion.
• Period: Max. Of 6 weeks.
• Authority: FR 101(a) and G.O.Ms.No.129,Fin,Dt.13.08.85
• Admissibility: Temp./Permanent employees
• Availment: on production of MC from RMP
• Effect: Counts for increment, pension
• Leave salary: salary on full pay
• Sanctioning Authority: H.O.O./ as delegated.
(B) Temporary: 15 days after 24 months gap (G.O.Ms.No.221,F and P(FR.I),Dt.23.08.74, G.O.Ms.No.316, F and P(FR.I), Dt.25.11.74(Sup.) Memo No.47774/1177/FR.I/74-1, Dt.07.11.74(Class IV), G.O.Ms.No.393, Fin., Dt.31.12.75(all)) • Effect : Surrendered days will be deducted in leave account.
• Validity: Sanction order is valid for 90 days from the date of issue. (Memo No.14423/715/FR.I/91, F and P, Dt.20.01.92 and Memo No.27/423/A2/FR.I/97-1, F and P Dt.18.08.97)
• Leave Salary:
(i) Claimed by considering 30 days/per month irrespective of claimed month. (G.O.Ms.No.306,F and P(FWFR.I) Dept., Dt.08.11.1974)
(ii) It includes Pay + OCA + HRA + AHRA + CCA. (Memo No. 64861/797/FR.I/71-1, Dt.14.07.72,G.O.Ms.No.25,F and P, Dt.05.02.96).
(iii) Conveyance allowance can not be paid (iv) HRA can be claimed to those who are residing in Govt. quarters. (G.O.Ms.No.337,F and P(FWPC.II) Dept., Dt.29.09.94) (v) No
Interim Relief will be paid (Memo No.31948/398/PCI/98-1,Fin, Dt.12.08.98)
(vi) Debitable to HOA 010-018. Sanctioning Authority: As delegated.

Others:
1. It is extended to Municipal Employees, Public Health Workers, Non Public Health Workers, Zilla parishad, Zilla Granthalay, employees, Village Secretaries
2. Surrender Leave amount may be initially paid by the Foreign Employer for those who are working in Foreign Service, and the total amount have to be reimbursed by the parent department later on. (G.O.Ms.No.329, F and P(FR.I) Dept.,Dt.06.12.74, Memo No.49395/1219/FR.I/75-1,F and P,Dt.06.01.76). Encashment of E.L.s:
3. The employees are permitted to encash E.L. at the time of superannuation / death / Voluntary retirement/Retirement on medical grounds/ compulsory retired as a measure of punishment under APCS(CCA) Rules and has been enhanced to, from 240 to 300 days w.e.f. 16.09.05.(G.O.Ms.No.27,F and P(FWFR.I), Dt.19.01.76) G.O.Ms.No:232,Fin.(FR.I) Dept,Dt.16.09.2005, G.O.Ms.No.234,Fin(FR.I) Dept.,Dt.11.08.06 w.e.f.16.09.05( die while in service)).
4. EEL may be withhold for those who are facing disciplinary proceedings until final settlement which involves recovery of money (G.O.Ms.No.11, F and P(FWFR.I)Dept.,Dt.15.01.97).
5. EEL encashment is to be sanctioned by the parent department for those who retired in foreign service.
</para_desc>
</para>

<para>
<para_name>COMMUTED LEAVE : </para_name>
<para_desc>
• Authority: AP LR Rules 15-B, 18-B • Admissibility: Permanent/ (Temporary Employees)*
• Availment: On medical grounds (MC) only Temporary employees after two/one year of service.
• Limitation: 240 days in entire service.
• Effect: Twice the amount of HPL will be deducted.
• Leave Salary: Double the half pay + all allowances in full
• Conversion of Commuted leave to HPL: When a Govt. servant intends to resign/retire after availing commuted leave, it should be converted into HPL and HPL salary should be recovered. An undertaking should be taken from employee whenever it is sanctioned (G.O.Ms.No.300, Fin., Dt.18.11.65).
</para_desc>
</para>

<para>
<para_name>EXTRAORDINARY LEAVE : </para_name>
<para_desc>
• Concept: Leave granted when no other leave is admissible, but it can also be granted even when other leave being admissible.
• Authority: FR 85, Rule 16,19,23(a)(ii) of APLR
• Admissibility: Temp./ Permanent
• Period: Not more than 5 years
• Availment:On personal affairs/on medical grounds
• Leave Salary: No salary
• Effect: EOL on MC counts for increment,pension EOL on pvt. Affairs – not count for increment, counted up to 3 years for pension, EL account will be deducted by 1/10th.
• Sanctioning Authority: Up to 6months – HOD above that – Govt.
• For Temporary Employees: EOL can be sanctioned for
(a) 3 months ordinarily in one occasion
(b) 6 months on MC by Govt.(3 yrs of service)
(c) 18 months for treatment of TB/Leprosy (1yr of service)
(d) 12 months for treatment of Cancer, mental illness
(e) 24 months for prosecuting studies certified to be in public interest and to employees of SC and ST to join pre examination training course at center notified by Govt.
</para_desc>
</para>

<para>
<para_name>SPECIAL DISABILITY LEAVE : </para_name>
<para_desc>
• Concept: Leave granted to a Govt. Servant who is disabled/injured or met with road accidents while on duty
• Authority: FR 83, 83A
• Eligibility: Temp. / Permanent employees
• Period: Upto 24 months
• Availment:
1. On producing MC For Gazetted- Medical Board NGOs - Civil Surgeon If it is below 2 months all – Govt.Medical Officer (G.O.Ms.No.40, Fin.,Dt.03.06.61)
2. Availed in combination with other leave.
3. Disability - manifested itself within 3 months of occurrence Relaxation: President of India
4. If the disability is aggravated, it may be granted more than once.
• Effect: Counts for increment, pension No debit of any leave.
• Leave Salary:
For Permanent upto 180 days – on full pay after 180 days- on half pay
For temporary upto 30 days – on full pay after 30 days- on half pay.
• Sanctioning Authority: Govt. Only For Police Personnel Upto 12 months – DGP (G.O.Ms.No.232, Home, Dt.22.08.98)
• Limitations:
1. The period shall not exceed 24months
2. Not admissible for road accidents while going to office from residence and vice versa.
</para_desc>
</para>

<para>
<para_name>MATERNITY LEAVE : </para_name>
<para_desc>
• Concept: Leave granted to female married Govt. servant having less than 2 surviving children (G.O.Ms.No.348, F and P(FWFR.I), Dt.05.11.77, G.O.Ms.No.219,F and P(FWFR.I), Dt.25.06.84,G.O.Ms.No.38, F and P, Dt.18.03.92)
• Authority: F.R. 101
• Admissibility: Temp./ Permanent
• Period: 180 days G.O.Ms.No.152,Fin(FR.I),Dt.04.05.10
• Availment: (prior to the date of delivery)* or after delivery, Can be combined with other leave with MC.
• Leave Salary: Full Pay + All allowances.
• Sanctioning Authority: H.O.O./ as delegated
• Note:
1. Extended to aided institutions (G.O.Ms.No.69,Sch.Edn(PS.I),Dt.06.06.03)
2. For contract employees 45 days with salary (G.O.Ms.No.197,WDCW and Dis. Wel.,Dt.14.05.03)
3. For Contract employees in Govt.Degree colleges 60 days(G.O.Ms.No.88,H.Edn(CE.I.1),Dt.09.08.11) without remuneration
4. For Contract employees in Govt. Jr.colleges 60 days(G.O.Rt.No.94,H.E.(I.E.-I), Dt.10.12.10) without remuneration.
5. For contract Pachayat Secretaries- 120days (G.O.Ms.No.254, PR and RD(Mdl.II), Dt.31.05.07) without remuneration.
</para_desc>
</para>


<para>
<para_name>LEAVE for employment abroad : </para_name>
<para_desc>
• Concept: Govt. employees desirous of seeking jobs abroad, irrespective of categories to which they belong technical, non-technical, or clerical be permitted to apply and secure employment abroad without applying for voluntary retirement or resigning from service. However, such of those scarce categories of staff/officers whose services are considered essential to this Govt. shall not be permitted to secure job abroad.
• Period: Not exceeding 5 years
• Authority:
1) G.O.Ms.No.214,F and P(FW.FRI), Dt.03.09.96
2) U.O.Note No.13127-A/113/FR I/98, Fin Dept., Dt.10.05.98.
Admissibility: Permanent employees with 5Yrs regular service.
Availment:
Upto 5 years in entire service in single stretch or in different spells (G.O.Ms.No.756,Fin(FR.I),Dt.07.08.02) Samples of materials shall be furnished at the contractor’s expense to the Executive Engineer when called for in the tender notice or ordered to be furnished by the Executive Engineer prior to execution of any work.
• Effect: The period of absence during employment abroad will be treated as EOL without allowances but shall not be treated as a break in service. It will not be counted for service benefits such as increments, pay, leave etc. However, if contribution towards pension is paid by the foreign employer or employee, such periods will count for pension.
• Leave salary: No salary
• Sanctioning authority: Govt. Only.
• This leave should not be utilised to secure job abroad, but should be utilised for undertaking employment abroad. (U.O.Note No.13127-A/113/FR.I/98, Fin. &amp; Plg. (FW.FR.I) Dept., Dt.13.05.98).
• The benefit of the scheme shall be given to Govt. employees at a single stretch or in different spells, but for a period not exceeding five years in all during the entire service. (G.O.Ms.No.756, Fin. (FR.I) Dept., Dt.07.08.02).
</para_desc>
</para>

<para>
<para_name>PATERNITY LEAVE : </para_name>
<para_desc>
• Concept: Leave granted to male married Govt. servant having less than 2 surviving children to take care of his wife.
• Period: 15 days
• Authority: G.O.Ms.No.231,Fin(FR.I), Dt.16.09.05.
• Admissibility: Temp./permanent employees
• Availing Procedure: 1.Prior to date of delivery 2.below 6 months after date of delivery on production of MC (Memo No.20129-C/454/FR I/2010,Fin,Dt21.07.10)
• Effect: counts for increment/pension
• Leave salary: on full pay
• Sanctioning Authority: as delegated.
</para_desc>
</para>

<para>
<para_name>Leave for Hysterectomy Operation : </para_name>
<para_desc>
• Concept: To undergo hysterectomy operation for female Govt. servant and hospitalization
• Period: 45 days
• Authority: G.O.Ms.No.52, Fin(FR.I),Dt.01.04.2011
• Admissibility: Temp./Permanent employees
• Availing Procedure : on production of Medical Certificate from Civil Surgeon
• Effect: counts for increment, pension
• Leave Salary: Salary on full pay
• Sanctioning Authority: H.O.O./ as delegated.
</para_desc>
</para>

<para>
<para_name>HOSPITAL LEAVE : </para_name>
<para_desc>
• Concept: Applicable to certain staff detailed in SR (2) under FR 101 (B). This leave is on half pay for a period not exceeding 6 months in every 3 years of service when detained in hospital and receiving medical aid as outpatient. It is not admissible when the treatment is necessitated by intemperance of an irregular habit.
• Period: Not exceeding 6 months in every 3 years of service
• Authority: FR 101 (b)
• Admissibility: Only Permanent employees
• Availing Procedure: on combination with any other leave
• Effect: counts for increment, pension
• Leave salary: first 3 months on full pay and next 3 months on half pay
• Sanctioning Authority: as delegated.
</para_desc>
</para>

<para>
<para_name>Child Care Leave : </para_name>
<para_desc>
Government have issued orders vide G.O.Ms.No.209, Fin. (HRM.III) Dept., Dt. 21.11.2016, for Child Care Leave for women employees for a period of 3 months, not exceeding 15 days in any spell in the entire service to look after two eldest children upto the age of 18 years (22 years in case of disabled children) for any of their needs like examinations, sickness etc. subject to the following conditions:
i) It shall be permitted only if the child is dependent on and residing with the Govt. servant.
ii) LTC cannot be availed during this leave
iii) The leave account for child care shall be maintained in the prescribed proforma and it shall be kept along with SB of the employee.
iv) The Head of Office shall ensure that the availment of child care leave to an employee will not affect the functioning of the office.
v) It requires prior sanction of competent authority.
vi) It may be combined of any kind of leave eligible including Maternity Leave, except with CL or SCL.
vii) It is admissible during the period of probation also. The period of probation shall be extended to that extent.
viii) The Leave Salary shall be paid on the pay drawn immediately before proceeding on leave.
</para_desc>
</para>

<para>
<para_name>MISCELLANEOUS RULES : </para_name>
<para_desc>
As per G.O.Ms.No:155: Fin (FR – i) Dept.,Dt:45-2010 Ex-Gratia Allowance to Government Employees on EOL for treatment for Leprosy/TB/Cancer Mental Illness /Heart Deceases/Kidney failure. (a) NGOs (Non Gazetted Officers) Pay not exceeding Rs 4550/- an ex-gratia allowance equal to half of his pay subject to a Min of Rs 1520/- and Max. of Rs 2190/- per month.whose drawing pay in R.P.S.1999.
(b) (Non-Gazetted Officers) Pay not exceeding Rs 6675/- an ex-gratia allowance equal to half of his pay subject to a Min of Rs 2960 and Max of Rs 4050/- per month. Whose drawing pay in R.P.S.2005.
(c) Non Gazetted Officers Pay not exceeding Rs 11,860/- an ex-gratia allowance equal to half of his pay subject to a Min of Rs 5770/- and Max of Rs 7490/- per month. Whose drawing pay in R.P.S.2010
Class IV Employees:
(a) Ex-gratia allowance equal to half of his pay subject to a Min of Rs 1270/- and Max of Rs 1920/- per month. (whose drawing pay in revised pay scales 1999).
(b) Ex-gratia allowance equal to half of his pay subject to a Min of Rs 2335/- and Max of Rs 3515/- per month. (whose drawing pay in revised pay scales 2005
(c) Ex-gratia allowance equal to half of his pay subject to a Min of Rs 4295/- and Max of Rs 6430/- per month. (whose drawing pay in revised pay scales 2010
</para_desc>
</para>

<para>
<para_name>Provisions of Leave in A.P.Fundamental Rules and Subsidiary Rules : </para_name>
<para_desc>
• Leave is dealt under F.R. 58 to 104, Chapter X, Part IV and Annexures of A.P. Fundamental Rules and Subsidiary Rules.
• Annexure III A.P. Leave Rules, 1933 (w.e.f.04.09.33)
• Annexure V Leave Calculator (Not Printed)
• Annexure V A Ready Reckoner for calculating Leave
• Annexure VI Model Leave Terms (Not Printed)
• Annexure VII Executive Instructions regarding ordinary CL and SCL.
• Annexure IX Case Law and Executive Instructions on Leave
• Annexure X Simplification and Liberalization of Leave Rules
• Annexure XI Surrender of EL Scheme.
• Annexure XII Compensatory Holidays.
• FR 58, 59 : Not printed.
• FR 60 : Leave is earned by duty only. A period spent in foreign service counts as duty, if leave salary contribution is paid.
• FR 61, 62, 63, 64 : Omitted.
• FR 65 : Carry Forward of Leave. Leave shall be carry forwarded for the former employees of local bodies who are appointed later through APPSC/DSC into Govt. service upto 31.12.13 vide G.O.Ms.No.46, Fin.(FR.I) Dept., Dt.19.02.14.
• FR 66 : The authorities competent to grant other than special disability leave to the Govt. servants working in each department.
• FR 67 : Leave cannot be claimed as a matter of right. When exigencies of the public service so require, discretion to refuse or revoke leave of any description is reserved with the sanctioning authority. But at the same time the competent authority cannot compel a Govt. servant to take leave on half pay when leave on full pay is permissible to him.
• FR 68 : Prefixing or Suffixing Leave ordinarily begins on the day on which transfer or charge is effected and ends on the day preceding the day on which charge is resumed.
• FR 69 : No employment on leave.
• FR 70 : Recall Compulsory – leave only up to the date of starting the journey Optional - no concession.
• FR 71 : Physical Fitness Certificate is required to report to duty after leave
• FR 72 : A Government servant on leave may not return to duty before the expiry of period of the leave granted to him, unless he is permitted to do so by the authority which granted him leave.
• FR 73 : Overstay after leave (AP LR 6 A)
• FR 74 : State Govt. may make rules regarding maintenance of records of service in order to secure efficiency and uniformity of Audit.
• FR 75 : Not printed
• FR 76 : Leave account shall be maintained for each Govt. servant.
• FR 77 : Not printed under Ruling Leave account for fraction of day should be rounded off to the nearest.
• FR 78 : Leave Account – Procedure of debiting
• FR 79 : Not printed
• FR 80 : The amount of leave due to Govt. servant is the balance of leave at his credit.
• FR 81 : Leave sanctioning Limit and procedure
• FR 82 : Vacation Department
• FR 83 : Special Disability Leave
• FR 84 : Study Leave
• FR 85 : Extra ordinary Leave
• FR 86 : Leave at credit – compulsory retirement
• FR 87 : Leave Salary
• FR 88 to 91 : Not printed
• FR 92 : Omitted
• FR 93 : Compensatory Allowances during Leave.
• FR 93A to 99 : Not printed
• FR 100 : Omitted
• FR 101 : Maternity Leave, Hospital Leave.
• FR 102 : Not printed
• FR 103 : Govt. – regulation of leave
• FR 104 : Apprentice persons – Leave.
• FR 55 : Leave may not be granted to a Govt. Servant under suspension.
• FR 18 : Max period of leave to be granted: 5 years
• FR 18A : A Govt. Servant shall be deemed to have resigned from the service if he
i) is absent without authorization for a period exceeding 1 year (or)
ii) remains absent from duty for a continuous period exceeding 5 years with or without leave (or)
iii) continues on foreign service beyond the period approved by the State Govt. (G.O.Ms.No.128, Fin(FR I) Dept. Dt.01.06.07).
</para_desc>
</para>

<para>
<para_name>Fundamental Rule 60 Extract : </para_name>
<para_desc>
FR 60 : Leave is earned by duty only. A period spent in foreign service counts as duty, if leave salary contribution is paid.
</para_desc>
</para>

<para>
<para_name>Fundamental Rule 65 Extract : </para_name>
<para_desc>
Leave shall be carry forwarded for the former employees of local bodies who are appointed later through APPSC/DSC into Govt. service upto 31.12.13 vide G.O.Ms.No.46, Fin.(FR.I) Dept., Dt.19.02.14.
</para_desc>
</para>

<para>
<para_name>Fundamental Rule 66 Extract : </para_name>
<para_desc>
The authorities competent to grant other than special disability leave to the Govt. servants working in each department.
</para_desc>
</para>

<para>
<para_name>Fundamental Rule 67 Extract : </para_name>
<para_desc>
Leave cannot be claimed as a matter of right. When exigencies of the public service so require, discretion to refuse or revoke leave of any description is reserved with the sanctioning authority. But at the same time the competent authority cannot compel a Govt. servant to take leave on half pay when leave on full pay is permissible to him.
</para_desc>
</para>

<para>
<para_name>Fundamental Rule 68 Extract : </para_name>
<para_desc>
Leave ordinarily begins on the day on which transfer of charge is affected and ends on the day on which the charge is resumed. Holidays can be prefixed or suffixed to leave subject to the conditions.

When public holidays have been allowed to be prefixed to HPL or EOL, if the competent authority is satisfied about its justification, he may allow salary during public holidays at the rates prevailing on the previous day. When the public holidays are allowed to be suffixed, as the leave would terminate before the public holidays, full salary as on duty may be allowed during public holidays suffixed. (Govt. Circular Memo No. 86595/1210/FR.I/7, Dt.29.05.81).

When a Govt. servant is certified medically fit for joining duty, holiday(s), if any, succeeding the day he is so certified (including that day) shall automatically be allowed to be suffixed to the leave, and holiday(s), if any proceeding the day he is so certified shall be treated as part of the leave. When the certificate is of a date intervening the holidays, the entire period of holidays may be treated as part of leave. (G.O.Ms.No.319, Fin. &amp; Plg., Dt.18.12.81) Local holidays notified in the district gazettes cannot be permitted to be prefixed to leave. (AG orders, Dt.13.09.40)

Public holidays allowed to be prefixed or suffixed, although they are treated as duty, postpone the period of probation, if availed during the period of probation. (Govt. Memo No.1688/64/GA/Services (A) Dept., Dt.04.07.1964). Similarly, vacation may be availed in combination or in continuation of any other kind of leave.
</para_desc>
</para>

<para>
<para_name>Fundamental Rule 69 Extract : </para_name>
<para_desc>
A Govt. servant on leave cannot take up any service or setting up of private practice etc., except with the permission of competent authority.
</para_desc>
</para>

<para>
<para_name>Fundamental Rule 70 Extract : </para_name>
<para_desc>
All orders recalling a Govt. servant to duty before the expiry of his leave shall state, whether return to duty is optional or compulsory. If the return to duty is optional, the Govt. servant is entitled to ‘No Concession’.
If it is compulsory, the period from the date on which he starts from the station to which he is ordered to join duty shall be treated as ‘duty’, but he shall draw leave salary until he joins his post, provided the leave that has been curtailed on account of such compulsory recall from leave is one month and above. He is also entitled to travelling allowance (Rule 87 TA Rules)
</para_desc>
</para>

<para>
<para_name>Fundamental Rule 71 Extract : </para_name>
<para_desc>
No Govt. servant who has been granted leave on Medical Certificate may return to duty without first producing a medical certificate of fitness in such for as the Govt. may by order prescribe.
</para_desc>
</para>

<para>
<para_name>Fundamental Rule 72 Extract : </para_name>
<para_desc>
A Govt. servant returning to duty before the expiry of leave should apply for permission to cancel the unexpired portion of leave.
</para_desc>
</para>

<para>
<para_name>Fundamental Rule 73 Extract : </para_name>
<para_desc>
(Over-stayed of Leave) A Govt. servant who remains absent after the end of his leave is entitled to no leave salary for the period of such absence, and that period will be debited against his leave account as though it is leave on half pay unless extension of leave is granted by the competent authority (LR 6A).
</para_desc>
</para>

<para>
<para_name>Fundamental Rule 74 Extract : </para_name>
<para_desc>
The application for grant of leave should specify the period of leave, nature of leave, leave address and in the case of leave on medical certificate, and the Medical certificates should be enclosed. (Rule 3 Annexure II).
If the leave required is on medical grounds, the application for the grant of leave shall be supported by a Medical Certificate (Rule 9 Annexure II).
No leave shall be granted to a Govt. servant when a competent punishing authority has decided to dismiss.
</para_desc>
</para>

<para>
<para_name>Fundamental Rule 76 Extract : </para_name>
<para_desc>A leave account shall be maintained for each Govt. servant.</para_desc>
</para>

<para>
<para_name>Fundamental Rule 77 Extract : </para_name>
<para_desc>
Fraction of a day should not appear in the leave account. Fractions below half should be ignored and those of half and more should be reckoned as one day (Ruling under FR 77)
</para_desc>
</para>

<para>
<para_name>Fundamental Rule 80 Extract : </para_name>
<para_desc>
The amount of leave due to a Govt. servant is the balance of leave at his credit in the leave account.
</para_desc>
</para>

<para>
<para_name>Fundamental Rule 81 Extract : </para_name>
<para_desc>
Leave may be granted to a Govt. servant at the discretion of the authority entitled to grant the leave.
The maximum period of continuous absence from duty on leave granted otherwise than on MC is 28 months. This period shall in no circumstances be exceeded by a Govt. servant who is on leave preparatory to retirement. (Ruling (d)).
</para_desc>
</para>

<para>
<para_name>Fundamental Rule 82 Extract : </para_name>
<para_desc>
Vacation is treated as duty for all purposes (FR 82(b)).
Any period of recess which exceeds 15 days in duration shall be treated as a vacation (SR2 FR 82)
If an employee enjoys not more than 15 days of vacation, he shall be considered to have availed himself of no portion of it. (SR6 FR 82)
If a Govt. servant of vacation department does duties during vacation and separately remunerated, he should not be considered as having been deprived of vacation. (SR 15 FR 82)
An employee transferred from vacation to non-vacation department is treated as in nonvacation department from the close of last vacation enjoyed; and on transfer from non-vacation to vacation department is treated as in vacation department from the date of expiry
of last vacation previous to such transfer (SR 7 and 18 of FR 82).
If earned leave is taken in combination of vacation, the total period of leave &amp; vacation should not exceed 180 days (Ruling 11 under FR 82).
</para_desc>
</para>

<para>
<para_name>Fundamental Rule 18 Extract : </para_name>
<para_desc>
Unless the Govt. servant in view of the exceptional circumstances of the case otherwise determine, no Govt. servant shall be granted leave of any kind for a continuous period exceeding five years (LR 5A)
A temporary Govt. servant working under emergency provisions who remains absent from duty after applying for leave or extension of leave to which he is not entitled to any leave unless the leave applied for is granted by Govt. in relaxation of relevant rules, he should be deemed to have been discharged from service (G.O.Ms.No.436, Finance, Dt.11.06.1957).
Wilful absence from duty not covered by the grant of any leave will be treated as Dies-Non for all purposes, viz. increment, leave, and pension (Note1 under LR 5).
Any kind of leave admissible under these rules may be granted in combination with any other kind of leave so admissible or in continuation with any other kind of leave so admissible or in continuation with any other kind of leave admissible or in continuation of leave already taken whether the same or of any kind (LR 6)
</para_desc>
</para>

<para>
<para_name>Fundamental Rule 18A Extract : </para_name>
<para_desc>
A Govt. servant shall be deemed to have resigned from the service if he
a) Is absent without authorization for a period of exceeding ‘one year’; or
b) Remains absent from duty for a continuous period of exceeding 5 years, with or without leave; or
c) Continues on Foreign Service beyond the period approved by the State Govt.

A reasonable opportunity to explain the reason for such absence or continuation on Foreign Service shall be given to the Govt. servant before the provisions of this sub rule are invoked.
(G.O.Ms.No.129, Fin.(FR.I), Dt.01.06.2007).
</para_desc>
</para>

<para>
<para_name>Fundamental Rule 55 Extract : </para_name>
<para_desc>
Leave may not be granted to Govt. servant under suspension.
</para_desc>
</para>

</ebook>